Robert Creeley Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Robert Creeley Papers.
undated, ca. 1940-1978.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Creeley, Robert.
1 linear foot.
Robert Creeley attended Harvard University, Black Mountain College and University of New Mexico. A member of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, Creeley has written novels, short stories, plays, screenplays, poetry, literary criticism and history. Creeley died in 2005.
MSS19780008
Biography
Robert Creeley was born 21 May 1926, in Arlington, Massachusetts, the son of Oscar Slade (a physician) and Genevieve (Jules) Creeley. He attended Holderness School in Plymouth, New Hampshire, before entering Harvard University (1943-1944 and 1945-1946), Black Mountain College (B.A., ca. 1955) and the University of New Mexico (M.A., 1960). From 1945-1946, he served with the American Field Service in India and Burma as an ambulance driver. A member of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, Creeley has written novels, short stories, plays, screenplays, poetry, literary criticism and history. Creeley has been awarded the Levinson Prize (1960), D. H. Lawrence fellowship (for summer writing, University of New Mexico, 1960), National Book Award nomination (1962, for For Love), Leviton-Blumenthal Prize (1964) Guggenheim fellowship in poetry (1964-1965, 1971), Rockefeller Foundation grant (1966), Union League Civic and Arts Foundation Prize (1967), Shelley Award (1981), Frost Medal (1987), National Endowment for the Arts grant (1982), Deutsche Auftauschdienst Programme (DADD, providing residency in Berlin, 1983 and 1987), Leone d'Oro Premio Speziale (Venice, 1985), Fulbright Award (1988, 1995), Walt Whitman citation of merit (1989), named New York State Poet (1989-91), distinguished award from State University of New York at Buffalo (1989), D.Litt, University of New Mexico (1993), Horst Bienek Preis fur Lyrick (Munich, 1993) and The America Award for Poetry (Washington, 1995).
Poet, novelist, short story writer, essayist, and editor, Creeley has had a varied career.
1950-1954 Founder and publisher, Divers Press, Palma, Mallorca, Spain
1954-1955 Instructor in English, Black Mountain College, Black Mountain, NC
1954-1957 Founder and editor, Black Mountain Review
1956-? Instructor at school for young boys, Albuquerque, NM
1961-1962 Instructor in English, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque
1963-1966 Lecturer, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque
1968-1969 and 1970-1971 Lecturer in Creative writing, San Francisco State College
1962-1963 Instructor in English, University of British Columbia, Vancouver
1963-1965 Lecturer in English, University of New Mexico
1965-1966 Visiting professor, State University of New York at Buffalo
1967-- Professor of English, State University of New York at Buffalo
1978-1980 Visiting professor, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque
1978-1989 David Gray Professor of Poetry and Letters, State University of New York at Buffalo
1985, 1986 Visiting professor, State University of New York at Binghamton
1988 Bicentennial chair of American studies, University of Helsinki, Finland
1990-- Capen Professor of Poetry and Humanities, State University of New York at Buffalo
1991-1992 Director of poetics program, State University of New York at Buffalo
Participated in numerous poetry readings and writers' conferences
Robert Creeley died 30 March 2005.
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of letters from Creeley to Jacob R. Leeds “Bob” (ca. 1940-1955), drafts of Creeley's stories and poems sent to Leeds, and Creeley's typescripts of poems written by Charles Olson, Vincent Ferrini, and others. Also includes Creeley's correspondence to others (1954-1978).
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( undated, 1940-1978 )
Series II: Poetry and Prose( undated, 194?-1950 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a numerous collections pertaining to the Beat Generation and Black Mountain College-affiliated authors. Additional papers of Robert Creeley are included in the following collections, also held in the Dodd Research Center: Papers of Bill Berkson, Fielding Dawson, Ed Dorn, Larry Eigner, Vincent Ferrini, James Koller, Joel Oppenheimer, Charles Olson, Tom Raworth, Michael Rumaker and Ed Sanders. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Writings by the Author:
Poetry
Le Fou, Golden Goose Press, 1952.
The Kind of Act Of, Divers Press (Palma, Mallorca, Spain), 1953.
The Immoral Proposition, Jonathan Williams, 1953.
A Snarling Garland of Xmas Verse (published anonymously), Divers Press, 1954.
All That Is Lovely in Men, Jonathan Williams, 1955.
(With others) Ferrin and Others, Gerhardt (Germany), 1955.
If You, Porpoise Bookshop, 1956.
The Whip, Migrant Books, 1957.
A Form of Women, Jargon Books, 1959.
For Love: Poems, 1950-1960, Scribner, 1962.
Distance, Terrence Williams, 1964.
Two Poems, Oyez, 1964.
Hi There!, Finial Press, 1965.
Words (eight poems), Perishable Press, 1965.
Poems, 1950-1965, Calder & Boyars, 1966.
About Women, Gemini, 1966.
For Joel, Perishable Press, 1966.
A Sight, Cape Coliard Press, 1967.
Words (eighty-four poems), Scribner, 1967.
Robert Creeley Reads (with recording), Turret Books, 1967.
The Finger, Black Sparrow Press, 1968, enlarged edition published as The Finger Poems, 1966-1969, Calder & Boyars, 1970.
5 Numbers (five poems), Poets Press, 1968, published as Numbers (text in English and German), translation by Klaus Reichert, Galerie Schmela (Dusseldorf, Germany), 1968.
The Charm: Early and Collected Poems, Perishable Press, 1968, expanded edition published as The Charm, Four Seasons Foundation, 1969.
Divisions and Other Early Poems, Perishable Press, 1968.
Pieces (fourteen poems), Black Sparrow Press, 1968.
The Boy (poem poster), Gallery Upstairs Press, 1968.
Mazatlan: Sea, Poets Press, 1969.
Pieces (seventy-two poems), Scribner, 1969.
Hero, Indianakatz, 1969.
A Wall, Bouwerie Editions, 1969.
For Betsy and Tom, Alternative Press, 1970.
For Benny and Sabrina, Samuel Charters, 1970.
America, Press of the Black Flag, 1970.
Christmas: May 10, 1970, Lockwood Memorial Library, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1970.
St. Martin's, Black Sparrow Press, 1971.
1-2-3-4-5-6-7-8-9-0, drawings by Arthur Okamura, Shambala, 1971.
Sea, Cranium Press, 1971.
For the Graduation, Cranium Press, 1971.
Change, Hermes Free Press, 1972.
One Day after Another, Alternative Press, 1972.
For My Mother: Genevieve Jules Creeley, 8 April 1887-7 October 1972 (limited edition), Sceptre Press, 1973.
His Idea, Coach House Press, 1973.
Kitchen, Wine Press, 1973.
Sitting Here, University of Connecticut Library, 1974.
Thirty Things, Black Sparrow Press, 1974.
Backwards, Sceptre Press, 1975.
Hello, Hawk Press, 1976, expanded edition published as Hello: A Journal, February 29-May 3, 1976, New Directions, 1978.
Away, Black Sparrow Press, 1976.
Presences (also see below), Scribner, 1976.
Selected Poems, Scribner, 1976.
Myself, Sceptre Press, 1977.
Later, Toothpaste, 1978, expanded edition, New Directions, 1979.
The Collected Poems of Robert Creeley, 1945-1975, University of California Press, 1982.
Echoes, Toothpaste, 1982.
Mirrors, New Directions, 1983.
Memories, Pig Press, 1984.
Memory Gardens, New Directions, 1986.
The Company, Burning Deck, 1988.
Window, edited by Richard Blevins, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1988.
Windows, New Directions Publishing Corporation, 1990.
Places, Shuffaloff Books, 1990.
Have a Heart, Limberlost Press, 1990.
Selected Poems, University of California Press, 1991.
A Poetry Anthology, Edmundson Art Foundation, 1992.
Echoes, New Directions Publishing Corporation, 1994.
Life & Death, New Directions (New York City), 1998.
So There: Poems 1976-1983, New Directions (New York City), 1998.
Also author of The Old Days and Gnomic Verses,both 1991.
Editor
Charles Olson, Mayan Letters, Divers Press, 1953.
(With Donald M. Allen, and contributor) New American Story, Grove, 1965.
(And author of introduction) Olson, Selected Writings, New Directions, 1966.
(With Allen, and contributor) The New Writing in the U.S.A., Penguin, 1967.
Whitman: Selected Poems, Penguin, 1973.
(And contributor) The Essential Burns, Ecco Press, 1989.
Tim Prythero, Peters Corporation, 1990.
Olson, Selected Poems, University of California Press, 1993.
Prose
The Gold Diggers (short stories), Divers Press, 1954, expanded edition published as The Gold Diggers and Other Stories, J. Calder, 1965.
The Island (novel), Scribner, 1963.
A Day Book (poems and prose), Scribner, 1972.
Mabel: A Story, and Other Prose (includes A Day Book and Presences), Calder & Boyars, 1976.
Collected Prose, Marion Boyars, 1984, corrected edition, University of California Press, 1988.
Nonfiction
“An American Sense” (essay) Sigma Press, 1965.
A Quick Graph: Collected Notes and Essays, edited by Donald M. Allen, Four Seasons Foundation, 1970.
Notebook, Bouwerie Editions, 1972.
A Sense of Measure (essays), Calder & Boyars, 1972.
“Inside Out” (lecture), Black Sparrow Press, 1973.
“The Creative” (lecture), Black Sparrow Press, 1973.
Was That a Real Poem and Other Essays, Four Seasons Foundation, 1979.
Collected Essays, University of California Press, 1989.
Autobiography, Hanuman Books, 1990.
Daybook of a Virtual Poet, Spuyten Duyvil (New York City), 1998.
Other
“Listen” (play; produced in London, 1972) Black Sparrow Press, 1972.
Contexts of Poetry: Interviews, 1961-1971, Four Seasons Foundation, 1973.
(Author of introduction) Judson Crews, Nolo Contendere (poems), Wings Press, 1978.
(Author of preface) Edward Dorn Selected Poems, edited by Donald Allen, Grey Fox Press, 1978.
Charles Olson and Robert Creeley: The Complete Correspondence, nine volumes, edited by George F. Butterick, Black Sparrow Press, 1980-90.
(Author of introduction) Diane Christian, Wide-Ons (poems), Synergistic Press, 1981.
(Author of afterword) Gilbert Sorrentino, Splendide-Hotel, Dalkey Archive Press, 1984.
(Author of introduction) William Corbett, The Collected Poems of William Corbett, National Poetry Foundation, 1984.
(Author of introduction) Robert Bertholf, Robert Duncan: A Descriptive Bibliography, Black Sparrow Press, 1986.
(Author of introduction) Butterick, The Collected Poems of George F. Butterick, edited by Richard Blevins, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1988.
(Author of foreword) Gerald Burns, A Thing about Language, Southern Illinois University Press, 1989.
Jane Hammond, Exit Art, 1989.
Irving Layton and Robert Creeley: The Complete Correspondence, edited by Ekbert Faas and Sabrina Reed, University of Toronto Press, 1990.
(Author of afterword) Michael Rumaker, Gringos and Other Stories: A New Edition, North Carolina Wesleyan College Press, 1991.
(Author of introduction) Louis Zukofsky,Complete Short Poetry, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991.
(Author of foreword) Diana L. Johnson, Denny Moers: Figments of a Landscape, Brown University, 1992.
(Contributor) Trevor Fairbrother, Brice Marden: Boston, Museum of Fine Arts (Boston), 1992.
(Author of preface) Jack Kerouac,Good Blond and Others, edited by Donald Allen, Grey Fox Press, 1993.
Tales Out of School: Selected Interviews, University of Michigan Press, 1993.
(Author of foreword) Martin Espada, Trumpets from the Islands of Their Eviction, revised and expanded edition, Bilingual Press, 1994.
Work represented in anthologies, including The New American Poetry: 1945-1960,edited by Allen, Grove, 1960; A Controversy of Poets,edited by Paris Leary and Robert Kelly, Doubleday, 1965; Norton Anthology of Modern Poetry,edited by Richard Ellmann and Robert O'Clair, Norton, 1973; The New Oxford Book of American Verse,edited by Ellmann, Oxford University Press, 1976; and Poets' Encyclopedia,edited by John Cage, Unmuzzled Ox Press, 1980. Contributor to literary periodicals, including Paris Review, Nation, Black Mountain Review, Origin, Yugen,and Big Table.
Source: Gale Database: Contemporary Authors
BIBLIOGRAPHY:
Books
Allen, Donald, editor, The New American Poetry: 1945-1960, Grove, 1960.
Allen, editor, Robert Creeley, Contexts of Poetry: Interviews, 1961-1971, Four Seasons Foundation, 1973.
Allen and Warren Tallman, editors, The Poetics of the New American Poetry, Grove, 1973.
Butterick, George F., editor, Charles Olson and Robert Creeley: The Complete Correspondence, Black Sparrow Press, 1980.
Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series, Volume 10, Gale, 1989.
Contemporary Literary Criticism, Volume 1, Gale, 1973, Volume 2, 1974, Volume 4, 1975, Volume 8, 1978, Volume 11, 1979, Volume 15, 1980, Volume 36, 1986.
Corman, Cid, editor, The Gist of Origin, Viking, 1975.
Edelberg, Cynthia Dubin, Robert Creeley's Poetry: A Critical Introduction, University of New Mexico Press, 1978.
Ford, Arthur L., Robert Creeley, Twayne, 1978.
Foster, Edward Halsey, Understanding the Black Mountain Poets, University of South Carolina Press (Columbia, SC), 1995.
Novik, Mary, Robert Creeley: An Inventory, 1945-1970, Kent State University Press, 1973.
Novik, Mary, Robert Creeley: An Inventory, 1945-1970, Kent State University Press, 1973.
Olson, Charles, Mayan Letters, edited by Creeley, Divers Press, 1953, Grossman, 1968.
Olson, The Human Universe, Auerhan, 1965.
Paul, Sherman, The Lost America of Love: Rereading Robert Creeley, Edward Dorn, and Robert Duncan, Louisiana State University Press, 1981.
Sheffler, Ronald Anthony, The Development of Robert Creeley's Poetry, University of Massachusetts, 1971.
Wilson, John, editor, Robert Creeley's Life and Work: A Sense of Increment, University of Michigan Press, 1987.
Periodicals
American Book Review, May/June, 1984.
American Poetry Review, November/December, 1976.
Atlantic, November, 1962; Atlantic, February, 1968; Atlantic, October, 1977.
Books Abroad, autumn, 1967.
Book Week, June 4, 1967.
Boundary 2, spring, 1975; spring and fall (special two-volume issue on Creeley), 1978.
Cambridge Quarterly, summer, 1969.
Canadian Forum, August, 1967; September, 1970.
Christian Science Monitor, October 9, 1969.
Commonweal, December 10, 1965.
Contemporary Literature, spring, 1972.
Critique, spring, 1964.
Encounter, February, 1969.
Fifties,Volume 2, 1959.
Harper's, August, 1967; September, 1983.
Hudson Review, summer, 1963; summer, 1967; spring, 1970; summer, 1977.
Iowa Review, spring, 1982.
Kenyon Review, spring, 1970.
Kulchur, Number 3, 1961.
Library Journal, September 1, 1979; April 15, 1994., p. 81
Listener, March 23, 1967.
London Magazine, June/July, 1973.
Los Angeles Times Book Review, April 17, 1983; October 30, 1983; March 4, 1984; June 24, 1984; June 23, 1991, p. 8.
Minnesota Review,Volume 8, number 2, 1968; Volume 9, number 1, 1969.
Modern Poetry Studies, winter, 1977.
Nation, August 25, 1962.
National Observer, October 30, 1967.
National Review, November 19, 1960.
New Leader, October 27, 1969.
New Republic, October 11, 1969; December 18, 1976.
New Statesman, August 6, 1965; March 10, 1987.
New York Review of Books, January 20, 1966; August 1, 1968.
New York Times, June 27, 1967.
New York Times Book Review, November 4, 1962; September 22, 1963; November 19, 1967; October 27, 1968; January 7, 1973; May 1, 1977; March 9, 1980; August 7, 1983; June 24, 1984; September 23, 1984.
Observer (London), September 6, 1970.
Open Letter, winter, 1976-77.
Paris Review, fall, 1968.
Parnassus, fall/winter, 1984.
Partisan Review, summer, 1968.
Poetry, March, 1954; May, 1958; September, 1958; March, 1963; April, 1964; August, 1966; January, 1968; March, 1968; August, 1968; May, 1970; December, 1970; September, 1984.
Publishers Weekly, March 18, 1968; March 28, 1994.
Sagetreib, Volume 1, number 3, 1982; Volume 3, number 2, 1984.
Saturday Review, August 4, 1962; December 11, 1965; June 3, 1967.
Sewanee Review, winter, 1961.
Southwest Review, winter, 1964.
Time, July 12, 1971.
Times Literary Supplement, March 16, 1967; August 7, 1970; November 12, 1970; December 11, 1970; May 20, 1977; May 30, 1980; February 20, 1981; November 4, 1983; May 10, 1991, p. 22.
Village Voice, October 22, 1958; December 10, 1979; November 25, 1981.
Voice Literary Supplement, September, 1991, p. 14.
Virginia Quarterly Review, summer, 1968; winter, 1972; spring, 1973.
Washington Post Book World, August 11, 1991, p. 13.
Western Humanities Review, spring, 1970.
World Literature Today, autumn, 1984; summer, 1992; spring, 1995.
Yale Review, October, 1962; December, 1969; spring, 1970.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Leed, Jacob, 1924—Correspondence.
Subjects:
Black Mountain Collection (Black Mountain, N.C.)—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; Black Mountain review (Black Mountain, N.C.: Periodical); American poetry—20th century.; Poetry—Editing.; American literature—20th century.; Poets, American—20th century.; American poetry—Periodicals.; Authors and publishers—United States.; Universities and colleges—North Carolina.; North Carolina—Cultural affairs—Literature.; North Carolina—Newspapers, periodicals and journalism.; Black Mountain (N.C.)—Education—Universities and colleges.; North Carolina—Education—Universities and colleges.; Poems.; Fiction.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.
Occupations:
Poet.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Portions of the collection were donated by Robert Creeley. Additional materials were from Robert Creeley and dealers.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, (undated, 1940-1978)
  - Incoming
    - Leed, Jacob R. “Bob”, ca. 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Pound, Dorothy (envelope only), 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing
    - Arcano, Michael, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Chapin, Hank B., 1962-1963 (Box 1:, Folder 4-5)
    - Gay, Karl, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Landreau, Anthony N., 1958-1966 (Box 1:, Folder 7-22)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 194? (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1946 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1947 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1948 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1949 (Box 1:, Folder 27-29)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 30-31)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1950 (Box 2:, Folder 32-33)
    - Leed, “Bob”, 1951-1955 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - Mason, Ronald, 1954 (Box 2:, Folder 35-38)
    - McGrath, Thomas, 1958 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - Morgan, John R., 1978 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - Rowan, J.R., 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
- Series II: Poetry and Prose, (undated, 194?-1950)
  - By Creeley
    - “Aphorisms”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - “As Now It Would be Snow”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - “Le Bonhomme”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 44)
    - “The Cemetery”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - “Dialogue: On Love and Existence”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - “Doggerel for O”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - “The Epic Expands”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - “Epithalamion”, 194? (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - “Fairy Tale” and “Poem”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - “Fragments from Pico Della Mirandola”, 1949 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
    - “France”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 52)
    - “Gangster”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 53)
    - “It has been now how long...”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 54)
    - “The Late Comer”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 55)
    - “Leo and the Wind”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 56)
    - “My Gradfater is Dead”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 57)
    - “The New Comer”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 58)
    - “Notes on Love”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 59)
    - “Otto Rank and Others”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 60)
    - “Pico Della Mirandola”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 61)
    - “Poems for Beginners”, 1948 (Box 2:, Folder 62)
    - “Poem for Bob Leed”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 63)
    - “Poem for Henry Miller”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 64)
    - “The Poor Season”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 65)
    - “Return”, 1946 (Box 2:, Folder 66)
    - “Selection from the Rocket Book of Verse”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 67)
    - “The Shade is Eloquence”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 68)
    - “Things have changed since Hannah died”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 69)
    - “To Address the Insipid”, 1949 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
    - “To Robert That He Maketh Much”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 71)
    - “To the One in the Gray Coat”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 72)
    - “Woodsville, N.H.”, 1948 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
  - By Others or Unattributed
    - Unattributed, [1950] (Box 2:, Folder 74)
    - “Ballad of the Goodly Fader”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 75)
    - “Forced into peculiarities”, [1950] (Box 2:, Folder 76)
    - “In Cold Hell” (Olson), [1950] (Box 2:, Folder 77)
    - “Zoo Scene” and ”Night”, 194? (Box 2:, Folder 78)